A Guide to the John W. Daniel Papers, 1874-1914
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John W. Daniel Papers, 1874-1914
The Library of Virginia
23923
25 leaves and 35 pages
John W. Daniel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 23 January 1953, from Glenna Anthony, Lynchburg, Virginia.
Biographical Information
John Warwick Daniel was born 5 September 1842 in Lynchburg, Virginia, to William Daniel, Jr. (1806-1873) and Sarah Ann Warwick Daniel (d. 1845). Daniel attended Lynchburg College and Locust Grove Academy, but left school when the Civil War began. Commissioned a lieutenant, he rose to the rank of major and received a crippling wound at the Battle of the Wilderness. After the Civil War, Daniel began practicing law and entered politics. He served in the House of Delegates from 1869 to 1871 and in the state Senate from 1875 to 1881. Daniel was elected United States Senator by the Virginia General Assembly in 1885 and served from 1887 until his death. He represented Lynchburg in the 1901-1902 state constitutional convention, and was considered a potential vice-presidential nominee at the 1904 Democratic National Convention. Daniel married Julia Elizabeth Murrell (1850-1937) 24 November 1869. He died 29 June 1910.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1874-1914, of John Warwick Daniel (1842-1910) of Lynchburg, Virginia, consisting of letters, 1881-1909, discussing Virginia and national politics, railroads, courts, military commissions, the Civil War, speaking opportunities for Daniel, and personal matters; note of argument, 1874, concerning a contested election for the 43rd Confress; an ad for Warm Springs, Virginia; pamphlets on banking and currency and on industrial education; answer of the Virginia State Corporation Commission in a law suit against it in the United States Circuit Court; price list for the Manchester Oil and Paint Company; and an unused envelope.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
John W. Daniel Papers, 1898-1904 (LVA accession 21589).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1888-1910 (LVA accession 21623).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1887-1910 (LVA accession 21636).
John W. Daniel Papers, 1893-1910 (LVA accession 21683).
John W. Daniel Letter, 18 July 1904 (LVA accession 27993).
Contents List
- Note of argument, 1874, by Don P. Halsey (1836-1883), counsel for the respondent, in the contested election case for 5th congressional district of Virginia between Christopher Yancey Thomas (1818-1879) and Alexander Mathews Davis (1833-1889) for a seat in the 43rd Congress.
- Advertisement, 1 May 1879, for Warm Springs, Virginia.
- Letter, 24 June 1881, from Joseph Stebbins of South Boston, Virginia, to Daniel proposing to extend the railroad line from Brookneal, Virginia through South Boston to Roxboro and Durham, North Carolina.
- Letter, 17 November 1881, from Robert A. Martin of Petersburg, Virginia, to Daniel regretting Daniel's loss in the Virginia's governor race.
- Letter, 26 June 1883, from J. W. Foster of Loudoun County, Virginia, to Daniel informing him that a writ had not been served, discussing a railroad extension, and apologizing for not writing due to his reelection bid.
- Circular letter, 29 July 1887, from E. Y. Loomis of the Loomis National Library Association encouraging businessmen to buy books, stationary, newspapers, and other products from his company, includes a Knights of Labor Reform Ticket supporting Samuel I. Hopkins of Lynchburg for Congress from the 6th district.
- Letter, 16 December 1895, from W. D. Chesterman of Richmond, Virginia, to Daniel regretting that he cannot attend the wedding of Daniel's daughter.
- Letter, 26 March 1896, from William A. Glasgow, Jr., of Roanoke, Virginia, to Daniel asking for Daniel's aid in getting the United States District Court relocated to Roanoke.
- Letter, 23 June 1898, from T. R. B. Wright of Tappahannock, Essex County, Virginia, asking for Daniel's help in getting his son Preston a commission in the army and appointment to General Thomas Rosser's staff during the Spanish-American War.
- Letter, 10 July 1904, from Grenville Gaines of Warrenton, Virginia, to Daniel praising his political actions.
- Letter, 4 April 1905, from S. D. Buck of Baltimore, Maryland, to Daniel concerning General Jubal A. Early's Shenandoah Valley campaign.
- Postcard, April 1905, from G. W. Beale of Northumberland County, Virginia, to Daniel stating that Richard B. Davis of Petersburg witnessed the Union Cavalry charge which took place at Appomattox Court House after cease fire orders had been issued.
- Letter, 21 July 1906, from W. W. Pendleton of Wytheville, Virginia, asking Daniel to send him a yearbook.
- Letter, 31 July 1906, from H. B. Trundle of Danville, Virginia, asking Daniel to deliver the annual memorial address to the Danville Elks Lodge in December 1906.
- Letter, 11 September 1906, from E. L. Hunter of King George County, Virginia, asking Daniel to provide a letter of introduction for Fielding L. Asleton of Washington state to Senator Samuel Henry Piles (1858-1940).
- Letter, 14 September 1906, from J. Taylor Ellyson (1847-1919), Lieutenant Governor of Virginia, to Daniel with a request that Daniel speak in Martinsville, Virginia, for congressional candidate E. W. Saunders (1860-1921).
- Letter, 24 December 1908, from Thomas W. Miller of Roanoke to Daniel thanking him for a copy of the International Law Digest, discussing a letter written by Stonewall Jackson, and planning for the 1908 elections.
- Letter, 9 March 1907, from J. H. Scott of Portsmouth, Virginia, asking Daniel for a large map of the United States, a copy of the latest Smithsonian annual report, the weekly patent office reports, and lists of the records of the army and navy.
- Letter, 26 July 1907, from Alvah H. Martin of Norfolk County, Virginia, thanking Daniel for a previous letter.
- Letter, 5 February 1908, from G. M. Peek thanking Daniel for his help in securing Peek a 2nd lieutenant's commission in the United States army.
- Letter, 17 December 1909, from Lucian H. Cocke of Roanoke, Virginia, encouraging Daniel accept an invitation to speak to the young businessmen of the First Baptist Church.
- Pamphlet, ca. 1914, supporting the Glass-Owen Banking and Currency Law, passed 23 December 1913 and resulted in the creation of the Federal Reserve.
- Pamphlet, no date, titled "An Appeal for Industrial Education."
- Answer, no date, of Robert R. Prentis, Joseph E. Willard, William F. Rhea, and R. T. Wilson of the Virginia State Corporation Commission in suit against them by the Louisville and Nashville Railroad in the United States Circuit Court, eastern district.
- Price list, no date, for the Manchester Oil and Paint Company, Manchester, Virginia.
- Unused envelope stamped with Daniel's name.